Mostafa A. Mohammed

 Permanent Address El-Zieton, Cairo,11321 Egypt

Summary

Talented and self-motivated data analyst with +2 years of experience. My experience area is Data Science and Big Data platforms and architecture with solid background knowledge from my master studying in informtics group in Nile University and my self learning online with proven certificates in Data Science and Big Data. Able to play a key role in analyzing problems and come up with creative solutions as well as producing methodologies and files for effective data management solutions. Now looking for a suitable Big Data Developer position with a ambitious company.

Working Experience

Data Analyst, Etisalat Egypt

Feb 2015- Present

- Provide data and analysis needed to Business Intelligence and Reporting Team members.
- Design and develop ETL Processes and Reports serving complicated transformation and data cleansing logic.
- Working on manipulating and making segmentation on streaming data to provide business with live events analysis.
- Respond to Business needs and translate into specifications(requirements gathering).
- Understanding of reporting structures and layouts using various enterprise reporting tools.
- Perform data analysis for both Source and Target Tables and Columns.
- Performing Analytics and Reconciliation activities
- Produce and maintain technical specification documents.
- Automation of daily, weekly, and monthly ETL processes.
- Ensuring data availability for Business Operational Reporting purpose.

Solution Developer, Mobiserve

Dec 2013 - Dec 2014

- Developed Enterprise System include CRM, CallCenter, Delvery, Collection and Operation(C#, VB.NET, SQL Server).
- Developed Barcode applications based on business hardware and integrate it with Company Enterprise solution(C#).
- Developed Reporting Module to support business CRM, Devlivery, Collection and Operation
- Developed Mobility Solution To Serve Delivery Service(Android).

Solution Developer, Karizma

June 2013 - Dec 2013

• Developed Web Application System for international school include Finance module, Attendence module, Timetable management module, E-learning module, Online testing module (C#, SQL).

Undergraduate Research Student, HCILAB Supervisor: Dr.Ayman Ezzat

June 2011 - Aug 2012

- Developed a new technique to interact with a big display screen.
- Designed an algorithm that detects circle gesture and gesture inside the circle like line gesture.

Certifications

• Data Science Specialization By Johns Hopkins University

1. Getting and Cleaning Data.

2. R Programming.

3. Data Scientists Toolbox.

coursera

• Big Data Specialization By University of California, San Diego

1. Hadoop Platform and Application Framework.

Coursero

2. Introduction to Big Data Analytics.

Coursera

Education

• Master Student, Informatics Group, Nile University, Sep 2014 - Present

• B.S. of Science in Computer Science, Faculty of Computers and Information Systems, Helwan University, May 2013

Grade: Very Good

Graduation Project

Designed a mobile app for recognizing the activities signals of the user and processing it into a meaningful health report. Grade: Excellent Supervisor: Dr.Waleed A.Yousef

- \bullet Technologies Used : Matlab, C# 4.0, OpenCV, Weka, Android .
- Methodologies Used: Basic Filters, Liner Classification Models, Classification algorithms.
- Achievements: Working on recognition the activity signal that comes from accelerometer and classify it into classes (walk , run , jump,..) applying Signal Processing and machine learning .

Technical Skills

Languages & technologies:

- Big Data Development(Spark, Map-Reduce, Pig, Hive, Sqoop and Oozie).
- R.
- C# , ASP.net.
- Java.
- C/C++.
- Matlab.
- Mathematics.
- Shell Programming.
- Latex.

DBMS:

- Teradata.
- Oracle.
- MS SQL server 2000/08.

ETL Tools:

- IBM Data Stage.
- Talend.

Operating Systems

- Windows 95 8.
- Ubuntu 7.04 -14.10.

Interests

- Data Science.
- Big Data analytics.
- Machine Learning and Data Mining.
- Data visualization.
- Mathematics.
- Statistics.
- Algorithms.
- Programming Languages.

Languages

• Arabic

Mother Tongue Very Good

• English

Selected Projects

- Geo RF: Geographical Dashboard for Radio Frequency team in Etisalat Egypt to review the Network and its details including (Sites, Sectors and Cells 2/3G) responsible for (Getting and cleansing data, Data Analysis and Data Quality).
- Geo Marketing: Geographical Dashboard for Marketing team in Etisalat Egypt to review the Customer activities including (Usage, Locations, Recharge Per area and Network Activity such as Dropped Calls) responsible for (Getting and cleansing data, Data Analysis and BI Reports).
- Staff commission: Interface Program for finance to Automate the commission for Etisalat Dealers and retails responsible for (Getting and cleansing data, Data Analysis and BI Reports).
- ERP System: ERP System include CRM, CallCenter, Delvery, Collection, Operation (C#, SQL).
- Delivery Mobility Solution: Android Application Serve Delivery Process Included Check authentication, Load Data, Insert Data Online, Track Runner Data, Get Customer Signature and capture documents images, Scan Barcode (Android, Webservice .Net).
- School Management: School management system manage everything related to education process its include Finance module, Attendance module, Timetable management module, E-learning module, Online testing module (C#, SQL).
- Character Recognition: Classifying handwritten digits in MNIST dataset using Perceptron algorithm and KNN to reproduce the results on the MNISTs web page and compare results (MATLAB).
- Data Visualization framework: Developing MATLAB framework for a Data Visualization similar to Ggobi that includes features like (map, Scatterplot, Barchart, parallel coordinates plots, Multidimensional scaling, tours).

Extra Curricular Activities

- Sep 2015 Present: Admin in Egyptian Big Data Geeks groups and Participated in introducing several Data Science and Big Data topics like introducing Hadoop platform architecture, Big Data echo-Systems and Data Science with R.
- Mar 2013 Mar 2014: Member of the Marketing committee of Rise which is an NGO its vision to raise and spread the awareness of research in Egypt, direct the spotlight on the importance of research, and promote research impacts on the Egyptian economy.
- Sept 2011 Aug 2013: participate in Recorded and edited full courses in my university to be available online.
- Sept 2009 May 2013: Admin in Interest groups and Participated in introducing several advanced computer science topics like Cryptology, Machine Learning, Probability and Statistics, Discrete Mathematics and Latex .

Personal Info

• Date of birth: 09/09/1992.

Nationality: Egyptian. Marital status: Married.

References

- Dr.Waleed A. Youssef, Assistant Professor, Faculty of Computers and Information, Helwan University. E-mail: wyousef@gwmail.gwu.edu.
- **Dr.Ayman Ezzat**, Assistant Professor, Faculty of Computers and Information, Helwan University. E-mail: ayman@fci.helwan.edu.eg
- Dr.Omar Hamdy, Assistant Professor, Faculty of Computers and Information, Helwan Universit. E-mail: omar.hamdy@fci.helwan.edu.eg